The year is 1995.
时间是1995年。
The Madrid Metro is 71 miles long.
马德里地铁全长71英里。
Enough to be the 56th longest metro in
足以成为当今世界第56长的地铁线路
the world today.
。
That's pretty good. Given that Madrid is
那相当不错。 鉴于马德里是
the 65th largest city in the world.
世界第65大城市。
But 1995 was special.
但1995年很特别。
It was the start of a revolution.
这是一场革命的开端。
In 12 years, the metro grew by 126
12 年内，该都会区扩展了 126
miles, about 203 kilometers.
英里，约 203 公里。
It is the fastest democratically grown
这是近年来发展速度最快的民主
metro system in recent memory.
地铁系统。
And the reason it could be built so fast
而它之所以能如此迅速地建成，
was because of one single reason.
原因只有一个。
It was cheap.
它很便宜。
This is the New York City Subway.
这是纽约地铁。
And this is the plan for New York's
这是纽约
Second Avenue Subway.
第二大道地铁的规划方案。
It is the most expensive subway ever
这是有史以来建造的最昂贵的地铁
built. Yet it's not even finished.
。 但它甚至还没有完成。
Just taking phases one and two together,
仅第一阶段和第二阶段加起来，
for 3 miles of track.
3 英里的轨道就要花费近 100 亿美元。
Compared with cities across the
与
Francisco, London, New York, Toronto,
旧金山、伦敦、纽约、多伦多
and Sydney,
和悉尼等英语世界城市相比，
Madrid has consistently stayed on top by
马德里凭借低廉的建筑成本一直保持领先地位
building so cheap.
。
It is one of the greatest examples of
这是
how to build public infrastructure
如何正确构建公共基础设施
[music] properly. This is a story about
（音乐）的最佳范例之一。 这是一个关于
infrastructure expansions in history,
历史上最伟大的公共基础设施扩建项目之一的故事，而这个项目是由
led by a team called the rodents.
一支被称为“啮齿动物”的团队领导的。   一群
Rodents that coordinated for weeks,
啮齿动物协调了数周，
meeting in local cafes, comparing notes,
在当地咖啡馆聚会，交流心得，
and drilling.
并进行练习。
This is a video on the genius design of
这是一段关于马德里地铁精妙设计的视频
Madrid's Metro.
。
This video is based on an article by Ben
本视频基于 Ben
Hopkinson in Works in Progress magazine,
Hopkinson 在《Works in Progress》杂志上发表的一篇文章，
and also uses [music] additional
并使用了
material from NYU's Transit Cost
纽约大学交通成本项目提供的[音乐]附加材料
Project. From 1936 until 1975, Spain was
。 从1936年到1975年，西班牙
ruled by dictator Francisco Franco.
由独裁者弗朗西斯科·佛朗哥统治。
After his death, [music] Spain became a
他去世后，西班牙成为了
democracy.
民主国家。
The country's new 1978 constitution
该国1978年新宪法
created 17 autonomous communities.
设立了17个自治区。
[music]
[音乐]
They function like an American or
它们像美国或
Canadian federal state.
加拿大的联邦制国家一样运作。
Each of them has an elected parliament,
每个社区都有民选议会，议会
which in turn chooses a president of the
再选举
community.
社区主席。
The community of Madrid includes the
马德里自治区包括
city [music] of Madrid and nearby cities
马德里市及周边
and towns.
城镇。
It's a little larger in size than the
它的面积比
American state of Delaware, but a little
美国特拉华州略大，但
smaller than the Île-de-France, which
比包括巴黎在内的法兰西岛略小
includes Paris.
。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; Its regional assembly collects taxes,
其地方议会征收税款，使其拥有
which gives it a roughly 30 billion euro
约 300 亿欧元的
budget.
预算。
per capita for comparison.
作为对比，这比伦敦的人均预算高出 68%。
One of its key functions
其主要职能
responsibilities is transport. [music]
职责之一是运输。  [音乐]
Madrid's regional assembly controls the
马德里地区议会控制着
for Madrid.
马德里地区的交通运输联盟。
The government financially controls and
政府对
oversees the Madrid Metro, light rail,
马德里地铁、轻轨
and buses.
和公交车进行财政控制和监管。
It has all of the levers to approve,
它拥有批准、
fund, and oversee a project.
资助和监督项目所需的所有权力。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; Since the first regional election in
自 1983 年马德里举行第一次地区选举以来
Madrid in 1983, the assembly had been
，议会一直
controlled by Joaquín Leguina's Spanish
由华金·莱吉纳领导的西班牙
Socialist Workers' Party,
工人社会党（
also known as PSOE.
又称 PSOE）控制。
But their rival, Alberto
但是他们的竞争对手，阿尔贝托·
Ruiz-Gallardón's [music] People's Party,
鲁伊斯-加利亚尔东的人民党（
PPP, was gaining.
PPP）正在崛起。
It looked like 1995 could be an
1995 年似乎是
opportunity for Gallardón [music]
Gallardón [音乐]
to finally capture the assembly.
最终赢得大会青睐的机会。
Both sides campaigned on pledges to
双方竞选时都承诺
expand the Metro,
扩建地铁，
but there was something strange. It
但其中却有些奇怪之处。 这
wasn't a debate about more or less
不是一场关于
public transit, it was a debate about
公共交通数量多少的辩论，而是
who could build the most. Ruiz-Gallardón
谁能建造最多的公共交通的辩论。 鲁伊斯-加利亚尔东
promised over 30 miles of Metro by the
承诺，到
next election, just 4 years away.
下次选举（仅剩 4 年时间）将建成超过 30 英里的地铁。
[music]
[音乐]
That was more than double the 14 miles
这比工人
that PSOE government had delivered in
社会党政府执政
the previous 15 years they were in
前 15 年所修建的 14 英里多了一倍多
power. [music]
。  [音乐]
The promise was convincing.
这个承诺很有说服力。
The PP were triumphant and won 54 seats,
人民党取得了胜利，赢得了 54 个席位，
[music] just over the 52 needed for a
略高于获得
majority.
多数席位所需的 52 个席位。
Alberto Ruiz-Gallardón was sworn in as
阿尔贝托·鲁伊斯-加拉东宣誓就任
Madrid's president.
马德里主席。
His promise was clear and he had all the
他的承诺很明确，他完全有
power to go and [music] build.
能力去发展音乐事业。
But that created a problem for
但这给加拉尔东带来了一个问题
Gallardón.
。
He actually had to do it.
他实际上不得不这么做。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; But he only had 4 years.
但他只有4年时间。
If he failed, his citizens knew exactly
如果他失败了，他的民众也清楚地知道
who to blame.
该怪谁。
In the wake of World War I,
第一次世界大战后，
&gt;&gt; [music]
纽约地铁的乘客数量远远超过了
than it could handle.
其承载能力。
They needed new lines.
他们需要新的生产线。
So, an engineer proposed an ambitious
于是，一位工程师提出了一个雄心勃勃的
plan for expanding the [music] metro.
扩建（音乐）地铁的计划。
It included a line going down Second
其中包括一条沿着第二
Avenue.
大道延伸的线路。
The rationale was clear.
理由很明确。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
on the east side of Manhattan, and it
曼哈顿东侧只有一条南北走向的地铁线路，而且
was overcrowded.
非常拥挤。
But right after the Board of
但就在
Transportation agreed to build it, the
交通委员会同意修建该项目后不久，
stock market crashed.
股市崩盘了。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; The expansion plan was kicked into the
扩建计划被搁置了
long grass.
。
After World War II, plans started
二战后，
[music] again, but funding was tight.
音乐事业重新启动，但资金紧张。
maintenance on the existing lines. The
现有线路急需资金进行维护。
city's Board of Estimate asked the state
市财政预算委员会要求州
legislature to relax their
立法机构放宽
constitutional debt limit, but that was
宪法规定的债务上限，但遭到
rejected.
拒绝。
At the same time, different boroughs
与此同时，各个行政区都
were organizing to defend their
在组织起来，捍卫自己
interests in any future subway building.
在未来地铁建设中的利益。
Legislators from the fast-growing
来自快速发展的
borough of Queens [music] feared that
皇后区的立法者们担心
the money was going towards the
这笔钱会用于
potential Second Avenue Subway, instead
潜在的第二大道地铁，而不是
of money going to their increasingly
用于缓解日益
congested subway lines.
拥挤的地铁线路。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; This push got concessions. A third of
这次努力取得了一些让步。 三分之一的
the trains would be diverted under the
列车将改道穿过
East River and through to Queens.
东河，直达皇后区。
This change alone increased the price of
仅这一变化就使项目成本增加了
the project by around 25%, but this
约 25%，但
attempt to build the Second Avenue
修建第二大道
Subway was derailed by the start of the
地铁的尝试却因朝鲜战争的爆发而搁浅
Korean War.
。
This led to massive construction
这导致建筑业出现大规模
inflation that [music] destroyed any
通货膨胀，[音乐]破坏了原本就捉襟见肘的预算下任何
chances of expensive projects going
昂贵项目得以推进的可能性
ahead, given already tight budgets.
。
Hope for the project was fading, with
该项目的希望逐渐破灭，《
the New York Times declaring it highly
纽约时报》宣称
improbable that the line would ever be
这条线路极不可能
built.
建成。
But a decade later, change came again,
但十年后，变革再次到来，
this time from Washington, D.C.
这次不是来自纽约市或奥尔巴尼，而是来自华盛顿特区。
Lyndon Johnson's Great Society pledged
林登·约翰逊的“伟大社会”计划承诺
federal money for public transit
为公共交通项目提供联邦资金，
projects with the creation of the
并在 1964 年成立了
predecessor of the Federal Transit
联邦交通管理局的前身。
Federal money could now fund half the
联邦资金现在可以承担
cost of new lines, and plans were dusted
新线路一半的费用，相关计划也因此重新
off. Ground was broken and four tunnel
启动。 破土动工，挖出了四个隧道
segments were dug.
段。
It looked like the Second Avenue Subway
第二大道地铁似乎真的要
might actually get built.
建成了。
But as construction got underway, new
但随着施工的进行，新的
problems emerged.
问题也随之出现。
Deindustrialization and New Yorkers
去工业化和纽约人
moving to the suburbs eroded the tax
迁往郊区削弱了
base at the same time that spending
税基，与此同时，支出
pressures were rising.
压力却在上升。
This was the city's worst financial
这是该市历史上最严重的金融
crisis.
危机。
work on the line in 1975. [music]
1975年，市长被迫下令停止该线路的施工。[音乐]
More than a decade passed with no
十多年过去了，没有任何
progress.
进展。   与
The parallel Lexington Avenue line
主线平行的莱克星顿大道线
became the most crowded subway line in
成为了美国最拥挤的地铁线路
America.
。
Eventually planners went back to the
最终，规划者们
drawing board in the late '80s.
在 80 年代末期重新开始制定方案。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; But it still took decades until the
但直到几十年后，
first trains were running 1.8 miles
第一列火车才在
under Second Avenue.
第二大道下方 1.8 英里处运行。
The full plan was divided into four
整个计划分为四个
phases, [music]
阶段，[音乐]
to date.
目前只完成了第一阶段。
The final two phases are currently
最后两个阶段目前还
unfunded, and no one knows if or when
没有资金，没有人知道它们是否会建设，或者何时
they'll be built.
建设。
The Second Avenue Subway was delayed by
第二大道地铁的建设因
wars, fiscal crises, cuts, and political
战争、财政危机、预算削减和政治
turnover.
更迭而延误。
It was handed off between 14 mayors and
它先后在14位市长和12位州长之间轮换过
12 governors.
。
No single [music] entity was directly
没有哪个音乐实体需要直接
publicly answerable for its completion.
公开对其完成负责。
Boroughs, mayors, states, and federal
各区、市长、州和联邦政府
governments all [music] pushed forward
都提出了相互
competing visions, and all held veto
竞争的愿景，并且都
power over plans.
对计划拥有否决权。
Like a group assignment without a due
就像一份没有截止日期的团队作业
date, there was no mandate and no one to
，既没有规定，也没有人需要为此
blame.
负责。
It took New York 90 years to build 1.8
纽约花了90年时间才修建了1.8
miles of track. Ruiz Gallardon had just
英里的铁轨。 鲁伊斯·加拉尔登只有
4 years to build 35 miles.
4 年时间来修建 35 英里。
But unlike in New York, where the
但与纽约不同，纽约
different levels of government all
各级政府都
pushed their own vision and each had
推行自己的方案，并且都拥有
veto powers, Madrid's setup gave him all
否决权，而马德里的体制赋予了他
the power he needed to oversee the
监督该项目所需的全部权力
project.
。
He set a clear strategic direction and
他制定了明确的战略方向，并
hired a team of nine engineers to run
聘请了九名工程师组成团队来执行该战略
it. Their leader was Manuel [music]
。 他们的领导者是曼努埃尔·
Melis Maynar,
梅利斯·梅纳尔（Manuel Melis Maynar），
a no-nonsense engineer more interested
一位务实的工程师，他更热衷
in building tunnels than being in front
于建造隧道，而不是在
of cameras.
镜头前表演。
He became the president of the Metro.
他成为了地铁公司的总裁。
In his office, there hung four pictures
在他的办公室里，挂着四幅
of giant TBM machines, a picture of the
巨型隧道掘进机的图片、一幅
Virgin Mary, and a photo of his wife and
圣母玛利亚的图片，以及一张他妻子和
three daughters.
三个女儿的照片。
With their permission, he put his life
征得他们的同意后，他暂停了自己的生活，全身心
on hold to carry out the project.
投入到这个项目中。
[music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; This is more than a job, it's our life.
这不仅仅是一份工作，这是我们的生活。
&gt;&gt; He would start work before 8:00 in the
他早上不到 8 点就开始工作
morning, often stopping at a
，经常在去
construction site on his way into the
办公室的路上顺道去建筑工地看看
office.
。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; His core team was made up of engineers.
他的核心团队由工程师组成。
They were nicknamed the rodents for
它们因其挖洞能力而被戏称为“啮齿动物”
their tunneling ability.
。
They would meet up in cafes to talk
他们会在咖啡馆碰面，
about subway construction together.
一起讨论地铁建设的问题。
[music]
[音乐]
Luis Galedón made it clear they had 4
路易斯·加莱东明确表示，他们有 4
years to finish because that's what he
年时间完成，因为这是他
promised.
承诺的。
Madrid and New York are both incredible
马德里和纽约都是非常值得一
cities to visit.
游的城市。
But if you're anything like me, the
但如果你和我一样，
friction of traveling is often the most
旅行中的摩擦往往是最
painful part.
痛苦的部分。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; That's why this video is sponsored by
这就是为什么这段视频由
Saleli. Though honestly, I was using
Saleli赞助的原因。 说实话，
Saleli long before they ever asked.
早在他们提出要求之前，我就一直在使用 Saleli 了。
I'll usually just buy an unlimited plan
我通常会买一个无限流量套餐，
and work remotely straight off my
然后直接用
phone's hotspot.
手机热点远程办公。
Saleli [music] is an eSIM app, a digital
Saleli [音乐] 是一款 eSIM 应用，即数字
SIM, so there's no physical card to
SIM 卡，因此无需更换实体卡
swap. You open the app, pick a data plan
。 你打开应用程序，选择
in over 200 countries, [music]
200 多个国家/地区的数据套餐，[音乐]，
and you've got data the moment you step
一下飞机就能使用数据流量
off the plane.
。
It even blocks sketchy [music] sites,
它甚至可以屏蔽可疑的[音乐]网站、
trackers, and ads.
追踪器和广告。   整个
The setup took me about 2 minutes.
设置过程大约花了2分钟。
So, download the Saleli app or go to
所以，下载 Saleli 应用或访问
saleli.com/hook [music] and use code
saleli.com/hook [音乐] 并使用代码
hook for an exclusive 50% off plan.
hook 即可享受专属 50% 折扣计划。
While Madrid's governance is simple, New
马德里的治理结构很简单，而
York is complicated. It has a prominent
纽约的治理结构却很复杂。 该市有一位颇具影响力的
mayor, but they don't control the MTA,
市长，但他们无法控制
which operates the subway.
运营地铁的 MTA（大都会运输署）。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; The power mostly sits with the governor.
权力主要掌握在州长手中。
The MTA gets funding to build from the
MTA的建设资金来自
federal government and from the state of
联邦政府和
New York. But to get funds, they have to
纽约州。 但要获得资金，他们必须
compete with other projects around the
与全国各地的其他项目竞争，
country and demonstrate they achieve
并证明他们实现了
federal government goals like buy
联邦政府的目标，例如购买
America, environmental policies, and
美国货、环境政策，以及
mandate more expensive union labor that
强制使用成本更高的工会劳动力，从而
increases costs.
增加成本。
The projects also have to convince
这些项目还必须说服
voters in upstate New York to pay for
纽约州北部的选民为
the project in the city.
该市的项目买单。
And then, when the MTA manages to get
然后，当 MTA 设法获得
funding, they have to essentially bribe
资金时，他们实际上不得不贿赂
the city government to improve roads,
市政府，以换取改善道路、
lay new sewer lines, or build parks in
铺设新的污水管道或建造公园，
exchange for letting them run the line
从而允许他们
through that area.
在该区域铺设线路。
In one case, they paid the city's parks
其中一个例子是，他们向市公园部门支付了
department $15 million
1500 万美元，
to use a third of a park temporarily to
临时使用公园的三分之一作为
get underground.
地下通道。
A parks official said, "A smart agency
一位公园官员表示：“一个精明的机构
is going to ask for as much as they can.
会尽可能地索要更多。
With no leverage, the subway builders
由于没有谈判筹码，地铁建设者
had to oblige.
不得不满足他们的要求。
All of the delays, haggling, and paying
所有的延误、讨价还价以及向
off different stakeholders just [music]
不同的利益相关者支付费用，都只会
add to the cost.
增加成本。
New York used to have an in-house
纽约市曾经拥有一个拥有1600名员工的内部
engineering and construction management
工程和施工管理
group with 1,600 employees.
团队。
But by the time the Second Avenue Subway
但到第二大道地铁
was underway,
开工时，
this workforce had shrunk to just 124.
这个团队已经缩减到只剩下124人。为了
Consultants were brought in to fill the
填补人员
gaps and carry out design work and
空缺，开展设计工作并
manage construction.
管理施工，市政府聘请了顾问。
More consultants were then needed to
之后，又需要更多的顾问来
oversee these consultants and manage
监督和管理这些顾问
them.
。
Because this was the largest project
由于这是
built in New York City for over 50
纽约市50
years, there was a lack of institutional
多年来最大的建设项目，市政府缺乏
knowledge of how to deliver.
如何交付项目的机构经验。
Every changing demand meant consultants
每一次需求的变化都意味着顾问们
had to go back to the drawing board,
不得不推倒重来，这导致
increasing their fees and delaying
他们的费用增加，工期也因此延误
construction.
。
Second Avenue Subway and the start of
第二大道地铁一期工程竣工到
the second phase.
二期工程开工之间间隔了9年。
In that time, all the built-up expertise
在这段时间里，随着团队的分散，所有积累的专业知识都
vanishes as teams disperse around the
消失殆尽。”
country and globe to work on other
国家和全球范围内的其他
projects.
项目都需要相关知识。
impossible once it's lost and requires a
一旦这些知识丢失，几乎不可能再获得，而且需要花费
lot of extra time and money to relearn.
大量额外的时间和金钱才能重新学习。
Luis Galardon and Melis knew that this
路易斯·加拉尔东和梅利斯知道这种
approach wouldn't work.
方法行不通。他们
&gt;&gt; No large firm of consulting engineers
没有聘请大型咨询工程公司
was hired as general project managers.
担任项目总经理。
It is the author's opinion that
作者认为，
experience in other cities and countries
其他城市和国家的经验
has shown that such an approach does not
表明，这种方法
actually produce savings in time and
实际上并不能节省时间和
cost. The project management of the
成本。
civil engineering and architectural
土木工程和建筑
elements was [music] carried out by just
部分的项目管理仅由
three chief engineers and six further
三位总工程师和六位其他
engineers, all of whom were direct
工程师负责，他们都是
employees of the Madrid regional
马德里自治区政府的直接雇员
government.
。
&gt;&gt; [music]
加拉尔东和梅利斯组建团队时着眼于
the long run with the goal of capturing
长远发展，目标是积累
any experience
经验
&gt;&gt; [music]
并将其应用于未来的项目。
The team was hired by Mintra, a public
该团队由
company run by the regional assembly.
自治区议会运营的公共公司Mintra聘用。
They weren't constrained by the civil
他们不受
service pay scales and could afford to
公务员薪酬标准的限制，能够
hire and retain [music] the best talent
聘请并留住最优秀的
in engineers.
工程师。
They would all be put to the test. All
他们都将面临考验。所有
construction projects come with risk.
建设项目都存在风险。
But with tunneling, the risks are
但隧道工程的风险尤为
severe.
严重。
Unexpected changes in soil composition
土壤成分的意外变化
can drive up costs or even worse cause a
会导致成本上升，甚至更糟的是，会导致
tunnel to collapse.
隧道坍塌。
Even if no one is killed or injured, a
即使无人伤亡，
collapse is a major disaster.
坍塌也是一场重大灾难。
Just a year before the Madrid Metro
就在马德里地铁
expansion started, construction of a new
扩建工程开工前一年，伦敦希思罗机场一条新铁路的建设就
went disastrously wrong when an
遭遇了灾难性的事故：一种
innovative [music] tunneling method led
创新的隧道施工方法
to a collapse of two tunnels.
导致两条隧道坍塌。
The collapse led to cost spiraling by
坍塌事故使成本飙升
hundreds of millions, tripling the
数亿英镑，预算翻了三倍，工期
budget and adding 2 years of delays.
延误了两年。即使
A tunnel does not even have to collapse
隧道没有坍塌，也会
in order to cause headaches. It's hard
引发各种问题。我们很难
to know beforehand what the conditions
预先了解
underground will be like.
地下的情况。
But cities like New York don't want to
但像纽约这样的城市不愿
take on all the risk, so they used
承担所有风险，因此他们采用
fixed-price contracts for the entire job
固定价格合同，并
and choose the lowest bid they can get.
选择最低报价。
This way the private sector assumes all
这样一来，所有风险都由私营部门承担
of the risk. But this has problems.
。但这存在问题。
In exchange for shouldering the risk,
作为承担风险的回报，
contractors will want to be paid much
承包商会要求更高的报酬
more. But because of the lowest bid,
。但由于是最低报价，
they can't always reflect that in their
他们无法总是在初始报价中体现这一点
initial pricing. However, should an
。不过，如果
unexpected challenge arise, they can
出现意外情况，他们可以
submit a change order which modifies the
提交变更单。 这会修改工程
scope, price, or timeline.
范围、价格或工期。
Since the city is locked into a
由于市政府受
contract, this often leads to costly
合同约束，这往往会导致代价高昂的
disputes that can be litigated in court.
纠纷，甚至可能诉诸法庭。
These can shut down work sites, causing
这些纠纷可能导致工地停工，
whole projects to grind to a halt, and
整个项目停滞不前，
ultimately add extra costs. Madrid could
最终增加额外成本。
not afford for construction to stop if
如果马德里想要在四年内完成项目，就不能承受停工的后果
they were to hit the 4-year target.
。
Melis knew the difficulties of
梅利斯深知施工的难点
construction were hidden underground. So
隐藏在地下。因此，
his team invested more time and money
他的团队前期投入了更多的时间和资金，
upfront to study what the requirements
研究
for each tunnel would be. The senior
每条隧道的具体要求。高级
project team included four geotechnical
项目团队包括四位岩土
experts who conducted in-depth soil
专家，他们进行了深入的土壤
investigation and monitoring to
勘察和监测，以
determine which tunneling method would
确定
be the most suitable for each section.
最适合每个隧道段的隧道施工方法。
Melis refused to use fixed-sum
梅利斯拒绝使用固定总价
contracts.
合同。
&gt;&gt; No tunneling project should be
任何隧道工程都不应该
contracted under a fixed lump-sum
采用固定总价
contract. If any problem does appear,
合同。一旦出现问题，很
litigation or arbitration is likely, and
可能需要诉讼或仲裁，而
wasted in this process.
这会浪费大量的时间和金钱。
&gt;&gt; Instead, Madrid used a different
因此，马德里采用了不同的
contract structure. There were still
合同结构。合同中仍然包含
fixed lump [music] sums, but also a bill
固定总价，但同时也列出了
of quantities, a list of agreed prices
工程量清单，即
for extra jobs contractors could be
承包商可以承担的额外工作的价格清单。
That way, any additional work could be
这样一来，任何额外的工作都可以
readily priced and [music] agreed to
很容易地定价，并
with contractors.
与承包商达成一致。
bid out there, though. Their strategy
不过，马德里并没有仅仅选择报价最低的。他们的策略
focused on value for money rather than
侧重于性价比，而不仅仅是
just cost.
成本。
The bid price from the company was
公司的报价
weighted to be only 30% [music] of the
在评估中只占30%
evaluation.
。
The remaining 70% was split between 20%
剩余的70%则由两部分组成：20%
for the project time and 50% [music]
用于项目工期，50%
for the technical merits of the bid and
用于投标的技术优势和
experience of the contractor. This meant
承包商的经验。这意味着
Madrid was getting more honest bids from
马德里能够从承包商那里获得更诚实的报价，
the contractors and they were able to
并且可以
choose the ones best suited for the job,
选择最适合这项工作的承包商，而
not just the cheapest that guaranteed
不仅仅是那些价格最低但质量却可能令人失望的承包商
lemons.
。
Gallardon and Melis had got their team
加拉尔东和梅利斯已经
and contracts assembled, but now they
组建了团队并签订了合同，但现在他们
had to start.
必须开始了。
There's an old idea in project
项目管理中有一个古老的理念
management that sums up the restrictions
概括了
for large projects.
大型项目的局限性：
Good, fast, or cheap. Choose two.
质量、速度和成本，三者只能选其二。
Consultants will tell you that if you
顾问会告诉你，如果你
want to build a high-quality metro, it
想建造一条高质量的地铁，
can either be quickly built or cheaply
要么快速建造，要么低成本
built, but not both.
建造，但两者不可兼得。
The Second Avenue Subway proved this
第二大道地铁证明了这一点。
rule. As cost started to mount, the plan
随着成本不断攀升，一次性
to deliver all the subway in one project
完成所有地铁建设的计划最终
fell apart. To save money, the MTA
失败。为了节省资金，纽约大都会运输署（MTA）将
sliced the project into four phases,
项目拆分为四个阶段，但目前
only one of which has been built. That
只完成了一个阶段。这
means trading off money for time.
意味着用金钱换取时间。
Environmental impact assessments are
环境影响评估
commonplace for infrastructure projects.
在基础设施项目中十分常见。
They're meant to give decision-makers a
其目的是让决策者
better idea over the tradeoffs involved
更好地了解建设过程中涉及的权衡取舍
in construction,
，
but they often stretch to thousands of
但通常需要数年时间、数千
pages in years of review before a
页的审查才能最终
decision is made. Even projects that are
做出决定。即使是
good for the environment, like public
像公共交通这样对环境有益的项目
transit, can be snared by endless
，也可能陷入无休止的
processes.
流程中。
The Second Avenue Subway took 9 years to
第二大道地铁
pass, from starting the environmental
从启动环境影响
statement process to its finished
评估流程到最终
project. Gallardon didn't have 9 [music]
竣工，耗时9年。加拉顿没有9
years, so the assembly passed a law that
年的时间，因此议会通过了一项法律，
allowed environmental assessments to be
允许
abbreviated in certain circumstances.
在某些情况下简化环境评估流程。
This was sensible.
这很明智。
Getting people to move in denser urban
让人们搬到人口更密集的城市
areas is the single easiest way to
地区是
improve emissions for residents, so you
改善居民排放的最简单方法，因此，我们
don't want counterproductive
不希望出现适得其反的
restrictions that end up keeping people
限制，最终导致人们仍然居住
in less dense surrounding towns that
在人口密度较低、
require car use. [music]
需要开车出行的周边城镇。
So, if a metro extension was planned in
所以，如果 由于地铁延伸线计划建在
an already established urban area, they
已开发的城区，他们
knew that the impacts nature would be
知道这样做对自然环境的影响会
lower [music] than building on
比在
undeveloped natural land. Urban, faster.
未开发的自然土地上建设要小。在城区，速度更快。在
Rural and new, the same amount of
乡村和新建地区，则需要同样的
caution.
谨慎。
With a streamlined assessment, the
通过简化的评估流程，
expansions could get confirmed within 5
扩建工程可以在5个月内获得批准，而
Britain or America.
英国或美国则需要数年时间。如果
Without the streamlined environmental
没有简化的环境
assessment process, sticking to the
评估流程，坚持
tight 4-year timelines would be
4年的严格工期是
impossible.
不可能的。
The assembly accelerated permitting and
议会加快了审批速度，并
removed multiple levels of review.
取消了多层审查。
&gt;&gt; [music]
线路由地区
transit authority and the Madrid Metro
交通管理局和马德里地铁
company before being signed off by the
公司确定，然后由
government of the community.
社区政府批准。
The permitting stayed at the regional
审批权仅限于地区
level, unlike American or British
一级，这与美国或英国的体系不同，在美英体系中，
government, including local, regional,
包括地方、区域
and national, can weigh in with their
和国家在内的多个政府层级都可以参与
priorities.
决策。
The Second Avenue Subway was also
第二大道地铁也
plagued by long back-and-forth
饱受漫长的反复
consultations. [music]
磋商之苦。
Over 100 meetings were held, but even
举行了100多次会议，但即使是
that level of engagement didn't stop
如此多的参与也未能阻止
legal objections. There was a lawsuit
法律诉讼。
from a local community group objecting
当地一个社区团体就
to a station entrance. Even though they
车站入口的建设提起了诉讼。 尽管他们
were in favor of the project, they
支持这个项目，但他们却
repeatedly unsuccessfully legal
不惜一切代价，屡次以法律手段
challenges [music]
挑战（音乐）条款，但都以失败告终
at all costs.
。
Luis Garrido had a different view about
路易斯·加里多对咨询的看法则截然不同
consultation. He saw his government and
。他认为，政府及其在
its metro building election promises as
地铁建设方面的竞选承诺代表了
the democratic will of the community.
社区的民主意志。
This meant that community engagement
这意味着
during the project was limited and
项目期间的社区参与是有限且
top-down. The metro planners would
自上而下的。地铁规划者只会
merely inform citizens and ask for
告知市民并征求有
targeted feedback, like the location of
针对性的反馈，例如
entrances to stations, but not general
车站入口的位置，而不会征求一般性
feedback, like whether the line should
意见，例如线路是否应该
go ahead or where it should run to. If a
继续建设或应该延伸到哪里。即使
few loud voices tried objecting, they
少数人提出反对意见，也会被
were ignored because the majority of
置之不理，因为大多数
voters were enthusiastic about the
选民对
building. Communities could request
地铁建设充满热情。社区可以要求
changes to the plan, but if the changes
修改方案，但如果修改会
increased the costs or added a delay,
增加成本或延误工期，
they would be turned down. But Madrid
就会被驳回。但马德里的做法
didn't just speed up the paperwork. In
不仅仅是加快审批流程。在
New York, the city that supposedly never
纽约这座号称不
sleeps, you need a permit for anything
眠之城，任何
that happens on weekends or after 6:00
在周末或工作日晚上6点后
p.m. and before 7:00 a.m. on weekdays.
至次日早上7点前进行的活动都需要获得许可。
The subway's work window usually runs
地铁的施工窗口通常
from 9:00 in the morning to 8:00 at
从……开始。 从早上9点到晚上8点
night, 11 hours a day.
，每天施工11个小时。
The NYC Department of Transport mandated
纽约市交通局规定，
open throughout construction.
施工期间至少要保持四条车道畅通。
But a band-aid is better ripped off.
但与其敷衍了事，不如干脆利落地解决。
In Madrid, disruption that may have
在马德里，原本可能
taken eight years instead took just
需要八年才能解决的交通中断问题，最终只用了
three.
三年就解决了。
In Madrid, everyone understood that
在马德里，每个人都明白，
there would be disruption on the streets
街道上的交通中断将会持续
for three or four months.
三到四个月。
An engineer by training, Melis not only
梅利斯是一位受过专业训练的工程师，
had the executive authority, but he
他不仅拥有行政权力，还将
applied his engineering expertise
自己的工程专业知识
directly to the project.
直接运用到项目中。
He was both the top decision-maker and a
他既是最高决策者，也是一位
hands-on engineer. To meet the target of
亲力亲为的工程师。为了
finishing construction within the
在
four-year electoral cycles, the standard
四年选举周期内完成建设，传统的只安排
method of having one tunneling crew
一个隧道施工队的做法
simply wouldn't do.
根本行不通。
Instead, Melis took the total amount of
梅利斯没有采用传统的施工方法，而是先计算出所需的隧道总长度，然后
it by how much a single team and
除以单个施工队和一台
tunneling machine can do.
隧道掘进机的掘进能力。
And then they hired that many teams and
接着，他们雇佣了相应数量的施工队，并
ran them all at the same time.
同时进行施工。
Breaking down a big project into
将一个大型项目分解成更
smaller, more manageable chunks drove
小、更易于管理的部分，促使各个
competition between the teams to see who
施工队之间展开竞争，看谁能以
could tunnel the fastest.
最快的速度完成隧道掘进。
After their shifts, the engineers would
工程师们在下班后会…​​… 大家
meet up over tapas to discuss their
聚在一起享用西班牙小吃，讨论各自的
challenges and successes.
挑战和成功。
It also meant that the metro project was
这也意味着地铁项目
not relying on one massive supplier,
不再依赖于一家大型供应商，
which would have leverage over the
从而避免了供应商对
direction of the project.
项目方向的影响力。表现
Teams that worked well could then be
出色的团队可以获得
rewarded with contracts for future
未来项目的合同作为奖励
projects.
。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; Galardon signed off Melis's expansive
加拉尔东批准了梅利斯庞大的
inventory.
库存清单。
He also made himself and his deputies
他还让自己和他的副手随时
available to quickly make decisions
待命，以便迅速做出
requiring political input, such as
需要政治参与的决策，例如
station locations or coordinating
车站选址或协调
between different parts of government.
政府不同部门之间的工作。
These were made within 24 hours,
这些决策在24小时内就能完成，而
other countries.
其他国家则需要数月甚至数年。
Melis had eight different tunneling
梅利斯安排了八台不同的隧道掘进
machines working around the clock.
机昼夜不停地运转。
In February 2001, a Madrid [music]
2001年2月，马德里地铁10号线延伸段的隧道[音乐]
tunnel broke the record for ground
打破了地面钻探速度的纪录，
the metro. 900 m of tunnel in a month.
一个月内掘进了900米的隧道。
New York's [music] tunneling failed to
纽约的[音乐]隧道掘进未能达到
match this. Their machines moved half as
这一水平。他们的机器移动
fast as Madrid's and took three times
速度只有马德里的一半，
longer to set up, but also used 50% more
设置时间却是马德里的三倍，而且由于工会合同中存在重复劳动，他们使用的工人数量也增加了50%
roles.
。
While New York fell victim to the
纽约最终陷入了三
trilemma between good, fast, and cheap,
难困境。 在优质、快捷、廉价这三者之间，
Madrid was different. They remembered
马德里的做法却有所不同。他们牢记
one other thing.
一点：
Time is also money.
时间就是金钱。
When you build fast, things can become
快速建设可以
cheaper.
降低成本。马德里
Second Avenue Subway. In that time,
第二大道地铁的建设耗时近百年。在此期间，
there were wars, economic crashes,
经历了战争、经济危机、
inflationary periods, and different
通货膨胀以及目标
administrations with flip-flopping
摇摆不定的各届政府，
all driving up costs.
所有这些都推高了成本。
Building quickly means that a project is
快速建设意味着项目
less exposed to external shocks that
受外部冲击的影响较小，这些冲击会
cause inflation or changes of direction.
导致通货膨胀或方向改变。
Expertise also compounds. As teams spend
专业知识也会不断积累。随着团队投入
time building, they gain an
建设，他们会逐渐
understanding of how to build
了解如何
effectively. Pausing or slowing down
高效建设。暂停或放缓
projects stops this development and
项目会阻碍这种发展，
forces lessons to be learned multiple
迫使人们反复吸取教训
times.
。
And the sooner a project opens, the
项目越早开通，
[music] sooner the benefits can be felt.
就能越早感受到效益。
&gt;&gt; Time is extremely important in
时间在
transportation projects. Every year
交通项目中至关重要。
after the first extension of Madrid
马德里地铁首条延伸线
Metro was commissioned, 170 million new
投入使用后，每年新增用户达1.7亿人次，
million hours in the Madrid region. The
为马德里地区节省了总计2300万小时。由此产生的
social savings can easily be estimated
社会效益可以很容易地估算
at an hourly value of about 12 euros,
为每小时约12欧元，
the average cost of employment. [music]
平均成本为…… 就业。[音乐]
This gives a yearly social saving in
这每年可为
Madrid of about 275 million euros, not
马德里节省约2.75亿欧元的社会开支，还不
including other social benefits such as
包括其他社会效益，例如
reduced traffic congestion, air
减少交通拥堵、空气
pollution,
污染、
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; or noise in the city center.
或市中心噪音。
&gt;&gt; If you choose good and fast, cheap can
如果选择优质高效的方案，成本自然会降低
follow.
。
But they also had to make sacrifices.
但他们也必须做出牺牲。
In Britain and America, new
在英国和美国，新的
infrastructure projects often come with
基础设施项目常常
promises that they will be the fastest,
承诺它们将是速度最快、
the grandest, and most innovative.
规模最大、最具创新性的。
Station costs are often the most
车站建设成本通常是
expensive part of the entire metro
整个地铁项目中成本最高的部分
project. [music]
。[音乐]
The Second Avenue Subway stations were
第二大道地铁站的情况有所
different. They were much larger. The
不同。它们规模更大。96
96th Street station is about 2.6 times
街站的长度大约是
longer than its platform. The other is
其站台长度的2.6倍。另一个车站的长度是它的
twice as long.
两倍。96
96th Street station is longer than the
街站的长度甚至超过了
Empire [music] State Building is tall.
帝国大厦的高度。[音乐]
For the Second Avenue Subway stations,
对于第二大道地铁站，
New York City Transit requested
纽约市交通局要求在地下车站建造
extensive storage, utility, and
大量的储藏室、公用设施间和
personnel rooms
人员休息室。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
They could ask for these rooms because
他们可以提出这样的要求，因为
they weren't the ones paying for them,
他们无需为此付费，
and the MTA had to give in because NYC
而纽约大都会运输署（MTA）不得不让步，因为如果纽约市
Transit could withhold approvals if they
交通局拒绝，他们可以拒绝批准。 他们并
didn't get what they wanted.
没有如愿以偿。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; All the stations were unique with
所有车站都独一无二，
different designs, proportions, numbers
设计、比例、
of elevators and escalators, and amount
电梯和自动扶梯的数量以及
of back of house space.
后台空间大小各不相同。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; This prevented vertical integration.
这阻碍了垂直整合。
Melis knew that building gargantuan
梅利斯深知，建造庞大
complex stations would cost time and
复杂的车站会耗费
money that Madrid did not have.
马德里所缺乏的时间和金钱。
&gt;&gt; How could a metro station should not be
如何才能避免将地铁站
confused with that for a museum or an
与博物馆或
emblematic building for the city?
城市标志性建筑混淆呢？
Several million people will move each
每天有数百万人穿梭于
day across the stations of the metro
地铁网络的各个车站
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]，
&gt;&gt; and the design must emphasize this fact
设计必须强调这一点，
giving easy and simple movements to the
为乘客提供
users from the street to the trains,
从街道到列车的便捷通道，
wide escalators and corridors and
宽敞的自动扶梯和走廊，
shallow stations and platforms. Design
以及浅站台。设计
should be focused on the needs of the
应以
users rather than on architectural
用户需求为中心，而非追求建筑
beauty or exotic materials and never on
美感或奇特材料，更不应以
the name of the architect.
建筑师的名气为中心。
&gt;&gt; As far as possible, Madrid stations were
马德里的车站尽可能地
standardized using copy and paste
采用复制粘贴的
designs.
设计进行标准化。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; They built the same skeleton while still
他们构建了相同的框架，同时又
giving room for variation for
根据
site-specific reasons.
场地具体情况留出了变化空间。
This simplified the engineering and
这简化了
design work required and the
所需的工程和设计工作，也使
construction crews would gain experience
施工团队积累了经验
and efficiency in building them.
，提高了效率。
The new stations are simple and
新的车站简洁明了， 这些
navigate. Busier stations have
车站可复制，而且易于导航。客流量较大的车站会
A far cheaper way to spruce up a station
摆放雕塑和壁画，增添特色。这
than building an architectural behemoth.
比建造庞然大物要便宜得多。
Luis Calvo and Melis did everything they
路易斯·卡尔沃和梅利斯竭尽所能
could to speed up planning and
加快规划和
construction.
建设。他们不负众望。在
run-up to the 1999 election.
1999年大选前夕，卡尔沃得以启用新的车站和线路。
At each opening he could point to a
每次启用，他都能指着
physical manifestation of his party's
自己政党取得的
success.
成就的实物证明。
The press ran positive stories
媒体纷纷报道地铁
describing how quickly the network was
网络快速
expanding and always included a photo of
扩张的正面消息，并总是刊登
Calvo at the openings.
卡尔沃在启用仪式上的照片。
These events got so plentiful that a
这些活动如此频繁，以至于一个
rival [music] political party even
竞争对手（音乐）政党都提出了
complained.
抗议。他们认为，
The openings were a misuse of the PP's
这些启用仪式是人民党滥用职权谋取
office for political gain.
政治利益的行为。
In the 1999 election, Calvo ran both on
在1999年的选举中，卡尔沃既以
the success of the past 4 years and on
过去四年的成就为竞选纲领，也
pledges to build even more in the next
承诺在未来四年建设更多设施
four.
。
Confident that the team he put together
他对自己组建的团队充满信心，相信他们
would keep delivering.
能够继续取得成功。
Years later, Calvo wrote that the
多年后，卡尔沃写道，
success of the initial metro expansions
最初地铁扩建的成功
led to
使
&gt;&gt; [music]
（音乐）成为最
&gt;&gt; one of the greatest demands we received,
伟大的成就之一。 我们收到的诉求是，
that the next expansion should go
下一次扩建应该延伸得
further, close to their workplace or
更远，靠近他们的工作场所或
their home. Everyone wanted to feel
家。每个人都希望
involved. With the upswell in support,
参与其中。随着支持率的上升，
the PP won the 1999 regional elections
人民党在1999年的地区选举中获胜，
&gt;&gt; [music]
并承诺进一步建设地铁。随后，
they went on to win the 2003 regional
他们又赢得了2003年的地区
elections, too, with even more metro
选举，并
building promised.
承诺建设更多地铁。
Since 1995, they have won every single
自1995年以来，他们赢得了马德里每一次
Madrid [music] regional election.
地区选举。
The metro expansion transformed the
地铁扩建改变了这座
city. The metro nearly tripled in size
城市。短短12年内，地铁规模几乎扩大了三倍
in just 12 years.
。
The metro is consistently popular with
地铁一直深受
its residents, with 75% of riders very
居民欢迎，75%的乘客
satisfied with the metro, much better
对地铁非常满意，远高于
than New York's 56% satisfaction rate.
纽约的56%。
And its per capita ridership is higher
而且，马德里的人均客流量
than London or New York. Madrid has
高于伦敦或纽约。马德里拥有
of any city in the world. It is a beacon
世界上公共交通半小时车程内可达区域最大的区域。对于
to any city that wants to improve its
任何想要改善
transport network. If American and
交通网络的城市来说，马德里都是一个典范。如果美国和
British cities could build at Madrid's
英国的城市能够像马德里一样投入巨资建设
cost, they would be transformed. New
，它们将会焕然一新。
York's Second Avenue Subway would be
纽约的第二大道 地铁项目应该
complete, not bumbling through phase two
顺利完工，而不是磕磕绊绊地进行四期工程中的第二期
of four.
。
These advances won't happen overnight,
这些进步不会一蹴而就，
building anything. But perhaps the most
任何建设项目都会面临挑战。但或许最
important lesson of all is to consider
重要的经验是，我们应该借鉴
how other places deliver large
其他地方如何开展大型
infrastructure projects.
基础设施项目。
By sharing best practices and engaging
通过分享最佳实践，并
with successful cities,
与成功的城市交流学习，
&gt;&gt; [music]
我们可以改进自身的
build.
建设方式。